[Music]
thank you
foreign
[Music]
greetings people of Earth I come in
peace
welcome to the 145th episode of the ask
Abhijit show I hope you are all doing
extremely well
um um so uh before we begin let us see
who all is there with us in the comments
in the live chat I can see opai Mahendra
surekha samarth sushant Anisha rudra
Kapil super Samosa
Ayan Singh Abhishek Krishna
Hindus
History exam tomorrow all the best sir
xkgb agent mayank tripathi srihari Arun
suhani
Young
um
Indian citizen summer pan Singh c4d to
Suman saurabh Raya Nandan abhinav
jitendra Divya foreign
[Music]
skanda
Shri Hari Arun Kapil mandar and lots of
other people Shaheen suhani Mazar Aditya
Kapil Aditi Raya and lots of other
people good evening good to all of you
so nice to see you also thank you so
much for being on the show tonight
because this is a more
and lots of the people so uh as you know
today I will take questions that you
have asked in the comments so let us
begin
let us begin let's see what questions we
have I'm sure there's a whole lot of
questions let us see what we have let's
begin with question number one I think
we will begin at the right place you
know what's what's going on in the world
right now
closer to home
um here we are here we are Ankit says I
messaged the Israeli Ambassador and
thanked him for his stand on Twitter and
I think many like me did that but then
but when I saw him tweeting a random
shoulder message screenshot that
somebody praised Hitler in this box I
mean what was the point of doing that
either he's naive or a very very clever
person I lost all my respect for that
man they just want unconditional support
from us unconditionally right so what
happened
okay so the Israeli Ambassador so we
know what happened earlier this week
there was this person who said something
extremely uh unfortunate he was the head
of he was appointed the head of the jury
of an International Film Festival in Goa
and he said that the Kashmir files movie
is all propaganda and so on so forth
something very unnecessary and annoying
he said it in the presence of the
Israeli Ambassador and a very highly
Minister Mr anurag takur and so on then
Mr adidi uh
Israeli ambassador to India went ahead
and laid out a whole tweet thread in
which he kind of called out
the the person who made these comments
the Israeli person who made the comments
and then yesterday before yesterday the
Israeli Ambassador goes ahead and tweets
something he says that I am receiving
various kinds of uh threats or or you
know abusive messages on in my Twitter
DM box direct messages and he put one of
the screenshots out there
so I'm gonna put it on on the screen but
uh do no be warned that it contains
abusive language I do not usually put
abusive language on this show but I'm
gonna do it for make an exception
because this is something that's already
there in public and I think you should
know so here's what the Israeli
Ambassador tweeted let me put that on
the screen right
um
thank you
one second give me a second
where are we all right
okay so this is Mr naur hilon he uh
tweeted this December 3 8 AM which is uh
yesterday 8 am in the morning he says I
just wanted to share one of my one of a
few DMs I got in this direction
according to this person's profile the
guy has a PHD interesting yeah yeah sure
and even though he doesn't deserve a
protection I have decided to delete his
identifying information because I'm so
so virtuous and so so much nicer than
him and then it says something about
Hitler and you know Hitler was a great
person so some nonsense like that yeah
we don't know who tweeted this who who
sent this message to Mr nor gilon there
is no identifying information Twitter is
a global platform it could be anybody
from anywhere in the world we don't know
who did this right
and yet this uh the Israeli
Ambassador went ahead and tweeted this
so he is saying that I am receiving
abusive messages
on Twitter and the implication is that
Indians are tweeting this at him or
Indians are messaging him like this yeah
so
that that's the kind of thing so let me
tell you first of all what he had
tweeted earlier so this was the the open
letter to nadablapi the following the
criticism of Kashmir files uh which we
know about yes
so uh I had spoken about this yesterday
in the Indian interest podcast last uh
24 hours before today yeah before right
now
and uh he calls out another lapid in
this tweet thread but he doesn't really
make any major uh you know
he doesn't really uh support India's
stand on Kashmir in this he doesn't
really uh uh
he doesn't
refute another lapis claim that uh
Kashmir finds his propaganda and so on
and so forth he's saying you should have
been a better guest but I'm not claiming
that what you are what you have said is
wrong and so on
some of the things that Mr nor Elon said
in this tweet thread and then he goes
ahead and tweets this
so he's trying to essentially
he's trying to shame India and Indians
saying that Indians tweet this sort of
stuff so we are victims and you guys are
victimizing us that's the kind of thing
he's done so I I tweeted this in
response I said that India has proudly
and magnanimously rescued and sheltered
helpless Jews for over for two thousand
years with zero anti-Semitism India
never has had any record of
anti-Semitism India is the only culture
that has sheltered Jews rescued Jews and
never ever been anti-semitic India's
only culture the only civilization that
has done that yeah a random Anonymous
screenshot means nothing and certainly
does not represent India and then I say
that instead of diffusing tensions
you're raising the temperature
Ambassador very disappointing because
that's precisely what he's doing and
then when I said then I went ahead and
tweeted some more Israeli Ambassador now
he loves tweet is an undiplomatic
unnecessary and uncalled for it is a
deliberate provocation an attempt to
shame India and Indians it hints at
ulterior motives
hidden agenda and I then I went so
people have been tweeting at me so I've
been responding to them so it's possible
that Israel as the vasal state which we
know it is
it is the US's state so maybe the the
basal State Israel is doing the
overloads bidding the U.S is bidding we
know that the U.S has been forcing EU
and NATO Nations to act against their
own national interests we know what's
happening since February the Americans
have been forcing Europe
don't act against their own national
interests I'm trusting them right so it
would not be surprising if the U.S is
now arm twisting Israel into sabotaging
its excellent relationship with India
it's very much possible the Israelis
have to do what the Americans tell them
especially in the field of foreign
policy and geopolitics
yes the Israelis have no option so yeah
it's possible
so then I the last tweet is that earlier
this week Ambassador gilon called out
nadav lapid for being a bad guest who's
being a bad guest now who's being the
the bad guest now right so that's the
deal that's what's happening it looks
like this Ambassador this person
is deliberately trying to raise tensions
raise the temperature and you know you
know create this atmosphere of hostility
and and being a victim and in Indians
are victimizing us that sort of thing
which is incredibly disappointing that
an ambassador would behave like this an
ambassador is a diploma diplomats know
how to behave in public what things to
say their statements are typically very
diplomatic and this is extremely
unfortunate and disappointing what he
has done it is not diploma this this
behavior is not the behavior of friendly
Nation or a diplomat right
so that's that's the situation that we
are in right now now uh let's let's go
ahead and see I said that India has
always rescued Jews sheltered Jews
helpless Jews Hill Jews have a have a
history of being helpless the past 2000
plus years yeah recently they've become
more less helpless because they have
their own Nation now which was created
uh for them by the British and the
Americans and the and as U.S was South
they have been able to uh do very well I
I yesterday I went ahead and said that I
do have the greatest admiration which is
respect for what Israel as a nation has
been able to achieve the past seven
since 1947-48 yes I do respect what they
have been able to achieve and I do
admire them for a lot of things
but the truth is that Israel is a U.S
basal State without the US's support
Israel would not have existed would not
have survived the the 20th century right
uh and India has never ever had a single
record in a single instance of
anti-Semitism India has always sheltered
Jews the helpless Jews right here's an
example this is from The Times of Israel
how the Indian Oscar Schindler took in 1
000 polish children Jewish children
during World War II yeah documentary
little Poland in India Chronicles the
selfless Rescue of Jewish and Christian
kids as India struggled for its own
independence so even when India was
struggling with foreign occupation with
the destruction of the Indian economy
and the destruction of Indian wholesale
plunder of India by the British even at
that time India was rescuing and
Sheltering helpless
Jewish and Christian children and who
who did that it was the Maharaja
um
also known as Jam sahib right he did
this selflessly he said that I am your
father these kids were all orphans here
they had lost their parents in second in
the second during the events of the
second World War mostly polish kids some
of them Christian many of them Jewish
yes
so the Maharaja went ahead and uh
uh in a princely state in Gujarat and he
decided to adopt these these children
for the time being and shelter them in
India and look after them as long as the
war unfolded yeah and even today some of
those kids still survive and they do
remember this very fondly and many of
them were Jews yes
Jewish refugees
so this was in 1942 and so on you can
you can read this article you can go
ahead and read the article yes
uh so yeah that that's one example of
how India has always been kind to the
Jews magnanimous to the Jews our India
has always sheltered the Jews and so it
is extremely disappointing that this
person the ambassador of Israel to India
goes ahead and makes this
unsubstantiated allegation in an attempt
to shame India and to shame in the
Indian people the Great Indian people
who have always been kind and
magnanimous to the Jewish people and to
the Israelis extremely disappointing it
hints at ulterior motives it looks like
somebody somewhere doesn't want India
and Israel to have a good relationship
and so so what are the possibilities
there are multiple possibilities which
which could possibly explain the
behavior of this person
one possibility is that he has gone
Rogue and he wants to become a social
media star and and you know he needs
attention so one of the ways of gaining
attention is to is to engage in such
stunts that is one possibility yeah
the second possibility is that he has
received directions to do this from up
top from his bosses so who are his
bosses he reports to the prime minister
of Israel or to the foreign minister of
Israel I mean he he reports to the
foreign minister of Israel yeah so
whoever is the foreign minister of
Israel is a very high ranking official
in Israel and the foreign minister would
not come up with a foreign policy on his
or her own or own it would come in the
direction of the Prime Minister of
Israel Who currently I would believe his
morally is Benjamin Netanyahu which is
very surprising because Benjamin
Netanyahu has a history of trying to uh
trying to ameliorate the relationship
between India and Israel he has been a
very strong proponent of a better India
Israel and stronger India as an Israel
relationships a relationship
so yeah so it's it's very strange very
perplexing and the third possibility is
that maybe it has come from somebody
higher than Benjamin Netanyahu maybe
it's come from somewhere else from the
overlord of Israel which is the United
States and I have spoken about this in
the past just a month or so ago I spoke
about this and the the somebody had
asked me a question I remember you can
watch this video that uh
is there a possibility no we know that
the kind of relationship with Indian is
in India and the US have now is not very
good India has not India has steadfastly
refused to to the
American line in the uh Russia Israel
Russia Ukraine conflict India is
pursuing an independent foreign policy
based on its own National interest the
Americans are not happy about this and
we know that France is part of the EU
France is part of NATO essentially
France is a U.S visal whether they like
it or not it's the truth and similarly
Israel is also a U.S for South State yes
so is it possible the question was that
India and Israel a relationship and the
India French relationship could change
and I believe I had said that yes there
is a strong possibility that things
could not go things may not stay the
same and things may perhaps go kind of
downhill to a certain extent I had said
this and here we are just a month later
we are seeing something like this
happening it's never happened before
India and Israel have had the warmest of
relations India and Israel has have so
much in common our national interests
align they converge to a significant
extent there is immense potential for
more robust ties between India and
Israel there's immense potential for
further cooperation and a strengthening
of the india-israel relationship in so
many different fields in agriculture in
technology in I.T in space in the
military domain in geostrategy I spoke
about these things yesterday and despite
that despite the fact that there is so
much potential for progress in India in
the India Israel relationship we are
witnessing this sort of behavior from
the Israeli Ambassador so this kind this
essentially tells us that something is
something is up
something is up something is fishy and I
wonder who is orchestrating all this it
doesn't make any sense for the Israelis
to go ahead and sabotage their
relationship with India
I would not say that the relationship
has nosedived or anything but the the
kind of tweet you see is is is not
be who it doesn't behoove the ambassador
of a friendly nation of a nation that
has a strong relationship with India it
is Unbecoming of a person in that
position yes so yeah this this seems to
hint that uh to to the fact that things
may not be completely all right yeah I
hope that it's it's just a flash in the
pan and I hope it's just a mistake by
the Ambassador I hope he retracts this
this statement and deletes this to this
tweet I'm not even asking for an apology
if you just read this tweet and move on
as if nothing happened and we will also
move on as everything happen but yeah
it's been two days that tweet is still
out there and he's kind of unapologetic
so something is up something is up so
maybe I was right that you know the
relationship between India and Israel
and the maybe some other relationship
also may change in the coming days
that's where we are so yeah that's the
deal right now and we will keep an eye
on this as we do next question
okay in the last episode you said that
the Israeli Ambassador neither denied
nor accepted Hindu genocide in Kashmir
how can he do that when the Indian
government itself hasn't recognized the
genocide till date is in this how
diplomacy Works imagine if he had said
that the genocide was true and even the
government of India would have gone
against him
Holocaust is well recognized in the
world and is obviously and obviously in
Israel what are my thoughts well you are
right sir so I do not expect
the ambassador of Israel to go ahead and
and you know assert that a genocide
happened in Kashmir also or and so on so
forth it's not his business to do that
nobody has asked him to do that yeah but
he should not
support
uh a claim that the Kashmir files is is
uh propaganda yeah so he kind of called
out the individual another lapid on that
but he did not refute nadablapid's claim
that uh the movie is propaganda so yeah
that so he the entire tweet threat that
he put out was very diplomatic yeah and
it kind of refused to take a stand and
kind of did not support India in in a
variety of ways which I spoke about in
detail yesterday you can you can take a
look at that but your larger point is
absolutely correct
India itself has not recognized
the fact that what happened in Kashmir
was a genocide yes India itself was not
recognized this and
it's it's a continuation of what
something that's happened over a
thousand years I called it the
Millennium of humiliation right
India has suffered the worst genocide in
human history in the past 1000 years I
would say at least
I don't know I think around 500 million
or more than that Indians would have
died over a period of nearly a
millennium yeah which includes the
turkic mediated genocide of India and
then the European Christian mediated
essentially British mediated genocide of
India the British killed at least 100
million Indians at least 100 million
Indians in just a few decades
to most likely they killed around 200
million Indians if you if you sum up if
you add up everything over over two
centuries you know
and the Turks the turkic Invaders and
occupiers of India over a period of
seven or eight centuries would have
killed in my opinion it's it's a
guesstimate
they would have killed around 500
million Indians I think I'm sure the
number doesn't make any sense to you but
if you sit down quietly without your
with your emotions on the side and try
to think about it and try to calculate
based on actual records you will see
that what I'm saying is very plausible
yeah so um
so the truth is that India has suffered
the worst genocide in human history and
the Indian government doesn't recognize
this India's textbooks don't speak about
it India's historians stay far away from
this topic and since India itself hasn't
recognized what it went through why
should we expect foreigners Outsiders to
care to bother
so what Rahul is saying over here is 100
percent correct why should we expect the
Israeli ambassador
to recognize the fact of what happened
in Kashmir or what happened in any other
place in India over any other period of
time it is for us to recognize this
first and I think it's because of
political experiences that this has
never been this that the politicians and
the governments have always steered
clear of this matter very sensitive
issue they call it it will create
communal tensions and all I don't
understand why I should create
Communications tensions we're not
talking about people today who did
anything
the people the citizens of India who
live in India today have nothing to do
with what happened
over the past 1000 years they are
the the
what they say is that it will create
communal tensions between Hindus and
Muslims because in some way you're
accusing Muslims of doing something
excuse me today's Muslims have nothing
to do with what happened in the past
1000 Years today's Muslims of today's
Indian Muslims are in no way responsible
whatsoever for what happened a thousand
in the past 1000 Years the people the
individuals the foreign occupiers and
oppressors who conducted the genocide
have nothing to do with India's Muslims
so um that's the deal but India itself
refuses to recognize the fact see India
India is a very strange
Society
India Society suffers from two
conditions two psychological conditions
first
post-traumatic stress disorder PTSD
India Society collectively suffers from
PTSD
post-traumatic stress disorder India
Society is is this is is it
has all these
pathologies and problems social problems
societal problems all these tensions and
divides
within the society
and these are all the consequence of the
of the oppression that we have suffered
over the past 1000 years
India Society has been distorted
all kinds of of evil has crept in from
outside
and that is a consequence of the past
1000 years of foreign occupation and the
total Destruction of India society and
culture in the way Society had evolved
over over thousands of years to operate
yeah
so that is PTSD post-traumatic stress
disorder we are now no longer under
foreign occupation more or less and yet
we are suffering from the consequences
that's PTSD so India Society India's
Society suffers from PTSD
and the second thing India Society
suffers from is amnesia no memory
of what happened why because our history
textbooks and our history teachers will
not teach us what really happened
so today's kids grow up knowing nothing
and they see all these problems and
Society so they blame themselves
they blame themselves and they blame
their ancestors that it's all because of
our own fault
that's the problem
and who will resolve this
the Indian government
whom we elect and to whom we pay taxes
it's their duties their job to do this
and they are not doing it
since 2014 people have been saying that
now it's time to do it but no they
refuse to do it so that is extremely
disappointing so what Rahul says is
correct why should we expect foreigners
who have nothing to do with us why
should we expect them to recognize what
happened in India we have to recognize
it first our government
should do it first and it's not done yet
so yeah correct absolutely correct
kaushal says is it true that Indian Jews
who traveled to Israel during its
Reformation days and even later were
highly marginalized and persecuted
please throw some light on this matter
interesting question you ask my friend
yes interesting question so Israel was
recreated in 1947-48 around that time
yes yeah there's a whole history behind
that if you want one of these days I
could talk about it yeah it's an
interesting story the Jews are roughly
3000 a year history and their their
original Homeland is what is current is
the region that is now roughly the
region that's currently Israel
the whole story in behind that so um
Israel was created
uh in 1947 1948 around that time yes and
then there was this concept of Aliyah
that all Jews have the right to return
the right of return to Israel so no
matter where you live in the world if
you are a Jewish person you have the
right to go and uh immigrate to Israel
and live there and the moment you reach
that the Israelis will give you certain
things like money and some some kind of
job or whatever based on your
qualifications and things like that and
try to integrate you into Israeli
Society so if you are a Jewish person no
matter where you are in the world no
matter what the color of your skin is
doesn't matter you have the right to go
and live in Israel and become an Israeli
citizen yeah so many Indians
so India like I said some time ago a few
minutes ago has been Sheltering Jews who
helped us Jews who came to India for
shelter for at least 2000 years
a whole bunch of Jews came to India
yehudis came to India after the
destruction of the uh Temple of Solomon
by at the hands of the Romans in around
what what year was was it was it 82 A.D
don't hold me to that date I think it
was 80 to 80 or somewhere around there
somewhere around that if you are
interested to look up the dates yourself
I don't I don't memorize everything so
so there was this uh entire persecution
of the Jews by the Romans the the Romans
had occupied the land they were great
conquerors they conquered Judea and the
many of these Jewish people were
expelled out of Judea and they were
forced to settle in various other parts
of the world in Europe in the Roman
Empire some of them escaped and came to
India yeah
so I think that's the first occasion in
which you find the Jewish refugees
arriving in India and India treated them
with great well what shall we say
magnanimity and gave them a place to
stay in India and did not force them to
convert to any other religion and become
whatever you you do you you be you you
do what you want and we will allow you
to live there India has always been like
that
so these people have been these the
original Jews who came around that time
have been living in India for around
around 2000 years and then there were
many other waves of uh refugees Jewish
refugees coming into India and then
later you had the baghdadi Jews the
Sassoon so where drugs Smugglers Etc and
all that there's a whole different story
who also lived in India
um and so on so forth yes
so there have been various Jewish
communities in various parts of India in
Malabar down south in Kerala
um in the Mumbai region and various
other parts of India yeah you can look
up the history if you if you're
interested I'll not go into the details
right now because that's not what we're
talking about so when Israel was
recreated
uh this opportunity arose for Jewish
people for the Jewish people of India to
possibly migrate to Israel because we
know what happened to India India was
destroyed completely
thoroughly by the British India was a
very it was a terrible place to live in
complete poverty destitution and then
you had the nehruvian era in which there
was no growth in India India's
incredible potential was stifled and
suppressed yes so it made sense for
people to get out of India for for for
better for a better future for
themselves and their families and the
children and their descendants
so
many of the Indian Jews decided to email
to move to Israel lots of Indian Jews
yeah and then the question is what
happened to those people shall we take a
look at that yeah
um let's put some of this uh interesting
material on the screen let's do that
what happened to India's Jews
what happened to India's Jews who went
to Israel
right so this is a um BBC News article
Israel's Indian Jews and their lives in
the quote unquote Promised Land
so uh in
so let's see what it says here return to
the promised land
the Bene Israeli population it thought
it is thought to number around 80 000.
they came from the Western Indian state
of Maharashtra so around 80 000
maharashtrian Jews went to Israel a few
of some of them migrated in the 50s and
60s
before leaving India they had ready to
return to the promised land by being
taught Hebrew and some Jewish prayers
and all that so they were hardly Jewish
at all
they were all Indian I mean they even
look Indian there's no no Israeli or
Jewish appearance yeah they look like
Indians
um
so um it did not go the migration did
not go as smoothly as hoped uh Mr
goodekar says that like many others of
his community his family were
discriminated against because of the
darker skin color and because they could
not speak fluent Hebrew so today the
dominant Jewish people in Israel are the
are the white so-called white Jews yeah
the European origin Jews there are two
kinds of views the Ashkenazi there are
many kinds of Jews obviously the
ashkenazim and the sephardim the
sephardim I believe are the brown
skinned original Jews the original Jews
were Middle Eastern people they were
brown skinned people they were not white
people
then a whole bunch of Jews were forced
to migrate to the Roman Empire to
various parts of Europe it's a whole
story because of the Romans and then
because of the Ottomans because of the
during the Crusades and all that and uh
during the time of salahuddin and so on
so forth there were various waves of
migrations yeah so then these Jews who
lived in Europe they obviously
intermingled with the locals over time
over centuries and they acquired a
European appearance so you will say that
most of the prominent Jews in Israel are
European origin Jews yeah
and then it's strange that despite the
Jews originally being a brown-skinned
people there was this there is today
discrimination against people against
Jews in Israel who are not white
so
yeah so there was discrimination there
were these people were allotted in an
inferior home built of asbestos and Tin
there Mr goodekar says his father often
regretted living the living their life
in India
but they had burned all their Bridges
with Mumbai uh there is more there is
more
other people also agreed that the
community faced discrimination as soon
as they arrived in the country
um there was a dog I don't think people
Israelis had seen Indians in the 1950s
they were the darkest group in Israel
which seems extraordinary today
uh grocery shop owners would give them
black bread telling them it was for
black people yes
um
the biggest crisis faced by the
community was in 1962 when a rabbinic
council decreed that the Bene Israelis
or Indian Israelis Indian Jews would
have to have their maternal ancestry
investigated if they wanted to marry
Jews from other communities which means
that they were
there was an attempt to prevent them
from marrying with other Jews within
Israel in Israel and they and something
like that and eventually the this thing
um eventually they finally succeeded in
seeing their demands fulfilled and so on
so that's one example of what happened
to the Indian origin Jews there is this
other article which is more recent
Indian Jews in Israel it wasn't the
promised land it's behind a paywall so
let me go to this Twitter thread by
ruchir Sharma
73 years ago in Israel made a promise to
Indian Jews it did not keep it invited
them to return to the promised land but
went back on its word sometimes with
heart-wrenching consequences many Indian
Jews packed up their lives in
livelihoods and made the Aliyah a
religious phrase that describes moving
to the land of Israel
they had no idea just how miserable they
would they would be the homes assigned
to Indian Jews were tents wooden huts
and Tin houses whereas European Jews
were assigned more permanent structures
including apartments and even fully
furnished Villas European Jews were put
up in hotels until permanent
accommodation could be allotted the
Jewish agency had promised education for
children but access to this too was
given along the lines of race Indian
children were given a primary education
whereas European children received a
university level education many Indian
Jews had could quit government jobs and
shut their businesses to settle in
Israel but the new positions they were
assigned were far inferior to what they
enjoyed in India and also far inferior
to their qualifications they were given
temporary work at low salaries in
healthcare also European Jews were given
priority they were given priority in the
allotment of hospital rooms even over
extremely sick Indians sometimes
non-european Jews were apparently turned
away and told to return later when the
patient needed more urgent care one
letter from an Indian due to the Israeli
government said promises Were Made To Us
by the Israeli authorities in India by
the Israeli authorities that work will
be given to us in Israel according to
our profession very good education to
our children and decent houses to stay
therefore we agreed to resign from our
very long service jobs over very good
homes in the education of our children
to come to Israel and find out
just the contrary of what was promised
to us and we are your victims by your
false promises we now appeal to all men
with Consciousness and in Fair name of
humanity to raise their voices and asked
why this why are the sephardis the brown
skin Jews and the Indians in particular
why are they treated like this
and and human living and what is our
future it is only is it only to fight
Wars for you all and nothing else right
one letter addressed to prime minister
nehru said we beg and pray honorable sir
God of Peace and Justice to help your
Indian children in distress and ask the
merciless rulers of Israel to repatriate
us to back to our dear Mother country
India long live India when Indian Jews
were all they asked for permission to
conduct peaceful Protestant Israel in
Jerusalem their request was denied so
they continued to write to the
governments and Prime Ministers of both
countries into human rights groups
highlighting this their plight and
asking for Relief and rescue but this
too posed a challenge is there Indian
Jews were questioned even about their
complaints to Human Rights bodies in the
into the Indian government
the Israeli authorities had apparently
threatened them with imprisonment if
they continued to write these letters of
complaint here's more Israel gave birth
control to his to Ethiopian Jews without
their consent that's called racism and
that's called human rights abuses
written the whole little hope of change
for Israel's marginalized groups
Ethiopian Israeli protester is arrested
in Jerusalem you can check this out more
racism in Israel the murder of a young
menashe immigrant the Menace are North
East Indian Jews they seem to believe
that they are Jews the Israelis have
done various investigations genetic
investigations tests and all and they've
been able to find absolutely no Jewish
or Hebrew I mean Jewish or Israeli
ancestry but they have agreed to give
these uh the so-called this people from
Northeast India essentially in in
Manipur and nagaland the how Kips Etc
the Israelis have decided to give them
citizenship and then see how they are
treated
for a Jewish teenager in Israel to beat
kick and stab a fellow fellow Jew to
death because of his facial features
because his facial features are viewed
as being different how is such a thing
even possible well it is possible if the
person looks like a Northeast Indian
person
so that's what Indian Jews are facing
there India's uh what is this India's
Jewish lost tribe faces hard times in
Israel you can read this as well what
they are facing what they are going
through the same racism the same
marginalization and discrimination
breaks silence to protest their
subjugation to NGO controlling their
Aliyah immigrants from India call out
shavai Israel which they say uses
intimidation to silence detractors the
private organization Delight denies the
allegations whatever dozens of members
of the community gathered in Tel Aviv to
protest what they described their
subject as their subjugation
and so on
addressing the racism that exists
towards the benign Menasha Community
these are North East Indians who believe
that they are Jews and so on so these
are this is just a sample a small sample
of what Indians face
in Israel
those Indians who have decided to uh
migrate to Israel because they have
apparently Jewish origin and for for a
better future because Israel is a first
world country and with better access
better education better lifestyle better
living standards and so on so that's the
real reason why people move to another
country yeah
so that's the kind of situation
that's the kind of these are the kind of
problems and and challenges that Indian
origin Jews face in Israel to this day
it's not something that happened in the
past
racism discrimination not only Indian
origin
Jews but African origin Jews Ethiopian
origin Jews and even the suffered in the
sephardim the brown skinned original
Jews even they faced this discrimination
from their fellow Jews because
the dominant
ethnicity the Jewish ethnicity is the
European Jews the ashkenism
that's the truth yes so yeah that's the
answer to your question if you are all
interested in knowing more do read it's
all available online
all right
okay next question Alka says Maldives in
Australia denied participating in the
Indian Ocean meet held by China
major embarrassment for China what do
you think interesting so yeah what
happened I don't think it's a major
embarrassment for China
I think it's a major embarrassment for
for who I think it's a major
embarrassment for the Indian media
because it's the Indian media that was
that was reporting that uh
that the that Maldives in Australia also
participated in this event for instance
let me show this so this I believe is an
article I had shared at the time I think
a week ago it's by NDTV big big surprise
yeah
and now they have edited the article
they have edited it at that time it was
saying 21 countries or something now
they've changed the headline to 19
countries and they have removed the
names of those two Nations no thanks
uh Maldives and Australia at that time
they had reported that Maldives in
Australia had participated so I think
it's a major embarrassment for the
substandard journalists
of India I'm not saying all Indian
journalists are substantive there are
some brilliant and really worthy
journalists in India but overall the
mainstream media is all you know what
the the standards are like so I think
it's a major embarrassment for the
Indian media houses and the journalists
who reported
this fiction
that the Maldives and Australia had
participated in this Indian Ocean meet
um thing by China
so yeah it's a good thing so the
Maldives
as we know until recently until you know
the past decade or so the Maldives were
strongly under China's influence and now
they have declined that it's emerged
that they declined they refused to
participate in this meeting which was
held by China excellent very good in
Australia obviously Australia is a
nation that feels extremely threatened
by China Australia and China the
relationship has deteriorated
deteriorated greatly over the past few
years Australia is a member of the Quad
which is India and the U.S and two was
all states of the US yes so um
so that is the situation that's what's
going on and yeah it's not very
surprising that these two Nations uh
chose not to get involved in this uh
chinese-led initiative so it's not a
major embarrassment for China the
Chinese don't feel embarrassed about
these things it's it's in even I would
not feel embarrassed if if you invite 25
countries and 21 only or only 19 come
it's fine it's their choice it's not
embarrassing they'll keep trying they'll
keep pushing
that's the kind of nation China is and
that's the kind of objectives they have
extremely they they are an expansionist
hegemonic imperialistic nation and we
will have to stay on our toes and do
everything in our power to push back
against their expansionism yeah right so
that's about that so yeah I thought I
should take this up and and clear
because at that time last week I had
also said because of the media reports
that the Maldives in Australia
participated in that in that event well
it's not so and good
Rama Lakshmi says what do you think of
the 48 000 year old frozen zombie virus
in Siberia oh so scary is scary viruses
are intact until they are in host so do
these viruses hold any threat if we are
contaminated or exposed in any way and
Manish says what's about this zombie
virus that came in the news recently is
that a threat for the human race will it
be as catastrophic as we see in the
movies oh I'm so scared a zombie virus
you know um as you all know I I have
done a lot of podcasts with ranveer on
the runway show yeah and I remember last
year in one of the first podcasts I did
with him I said something which was
rather unfortunate I said that this
could be the decade of the virus
when I did this podcast with India was
still in under a situation of lock quasi
lockdown situation it was kind of iffy
whether we should go out in trouble or
not yeah
so yeah the virus was very much there
the the pandemic was very much on at the
time and at that time we had this
discussion and I had said that this
could actually be the decade of the
virus
I so hope it's not the case I so hope so
I so hope that this is not the decade of
the virus we've had enough of viruses
one was enough we don't want more and
now we see this news so what is the deal
what is this thing about let's let's put
the let's put a news report on the
screen
zombie virus ooh so scary I don't like
okay let me put it on the screen
okay a few uh news reports about what's
happened look at this Fox News
scientists revive 48.5 000 year old
zombie virus
from Siberian permafrost
so what's the permafrost
see if you um the permafrost region is
that part of the um of the ground that
is permanently Frozen so if you go to
higher latitudes if you go to higher
latitudes in the earth you know near the
Arctic Circle and all in the in the
Siberian region Etc the ground is
permanently Frozen because it's so cold
there so that is called the permafrost
that region where the ground is
permanently always Frozen 12 months of
the year even in summer it doesn't thaw
it stays Frozen
so that's the permafrost but now because
of global warming some of this
permafrost is beginning to to thaw
and then what happens is that the ice
melt the snow melts and the ground
unfreezes it thaws and whatever was
trapped in the ground for thousands and
thousands of years it kind of gets
untrapped and it may
it may get exposed to the atmosphere and
whatever is in there may make its way
out into the world
so you will find perhaps carcasses you
know Frozen Frozen carcasses of mammoths
and other other Ice Age animals that's
interesting but you will also find
viruses and bacteria and stuff like that
and other parasites you may find some
ancient plants coming back to life
possibly
but what really concerns us is that you
may see ancient microorganisms
uh coming out into the open again and
you know the thing is some
microorganisms can stay dormant but
alive
for not just thousands of years but
millions of years here's an example
look at this bacteria so this is a
report from 2021 Scientific American
bacteria in 100 million year old
seafloor sediment have been resuscitated
these bacteria were entombed
in the sediment
under the sea
so it's essentially bacteria encased in
Rock
essentially that's what it is and this
sediment was a hundred million years old
so this bacteria had been trapped inside
for a hundred million years
a hundred million years and these have
been resuscitated they have come back to
life
and I have seen other reports as well in
which uh people drilled you know
hundreds of meters underground into the
Bedrock
of the of the Earth
the pulled out course the samples of a
rock which were like hundreds of meters
underground and this rock was obviously
you know it had been under down there
for hundreds of millions of years and
they found bacteria in there and those
bacteria where they were able to
reanimate those bacteria
so bacteria
can remain dormant for hundreds of
millions of years and not dying
and that indicates that that would tell
us that you know it's possible to bring
back very ancient bacteria back to life
just imagine how scary that is and
similarly viruses viruses are well very
strange creatures they are
I mean it's not sure how to classify
them
they exhibit some characteristics of
living beings
and they also exhibit some
characteristics of non-living beings so
viruses are on the dividing line between
life and and between between living
beings and non-living beings
so viruses also can survive for a very
long time
the only thing is that they have they
have RNA and DNA and all that yeah
viruses so yes so now these scientists
whoever they are have revived these
ancient zombie viruses Frozen for eons
and Siberia this is the actual
scientific research paper an update on
eukaryotic viruses revived from ancient
permafrost yeah so yeah that's what's
happened very ancient virus has been
viruses have been revived not just one
but multiple viruses so yeah we would
call them zombie viruses and all that so
is this dangerous yes of course it is
potentially dangerous
is it we know less than one percent of
all viruses you take a spoonful or a
glass full of sea water it contains all
kinds of unknown viruses viruses that
have never been you know uh classified
and viruses that have never been studied
so viruses are all around us
most of the viruses we don't even know
what they are and scientists have never
even studied them so viruses are all
around us microorganisms are all around
us bacteria are all around us and so on
so forth
and we have evolved on this planet for
millions of years for billions of years
I mean our ancestors were shrew-like
creatures 66 million million years ago
when the non-avian dinosaurs went kaboom
and even before that our ancestors lived
so we
our origin goes back to the very first
Primal life on Earth you know 3.77
billion years ago
so we have survived 3.77 billion years
at least on the planet and we have we
have evolved in such a way that we know
how to deal with these various viruses
and bacteria and yet some of them if
they have not been around for thousands
of years or maybe tens of thousands
hundreds of thousands of years then they
could pose a significant threat to us
I would not say that a new virus comes
out and kills of all Humanity but yeah
it could cause a significant problem
like what we have just experienced and
we don't want that so I think that these
frozen zombie viruses are very dangerous
potentially very dangerous and these
scientists who are
studying them should exercise the utmost
quotient please for the sake of the Gods
please exercise as much caution as you
can we do not want a repeat of 2019 2020
and so on
the Chinese are still struggling with
that we do not want any new virus please
please for the sake of the gods don't do
that all right
says
people like Ian Hancock talk about Egypt
Indonesia turkey uh the Mounds in
America Etc but never ever talk about
Bharat why major biases against India
this is why I do not like Hancock and
all these other studies on programs like
Gaia Etc they all talk about the
in-house the Mayas the Egypt
et cetera but nothing about India
crickets yeah absolutely horrible and
ridiculous and I agree with purnima so I
I believe that uh Graham Hancock
actually did visit India on a couple of
occasions if I'm not mistaken many years
ago and it is likely that he even wrote
about it in one of his books that was
published early in the 21st century 2002
2003 or something long ago
I believe he had dived around the the
the
archaeological site of ancient dwarka
and all that a long time ago once or
twice
uh and at some point in time he even
wrote about it but if you look at the
latest uh TV series that he has come up
with ancient apocalypse he doesn't refer
to India at all and he actually claims
that Zoroastrianism is possibly the
oldest religion in the world which is
actually laughable yes so yes it is kind
of strange and disappointing that Graham
Hancock has this attitude he was not
always like this but yes he has chosen
to uh disregard India we know I think
everyone in the world knows that India
is the oldest known civilization and
also the oldest surviving civilization
in the whole world
so yeah I spoke about this a couple of
weeks ago as well I'm sure I kind of
reviewed very cursorly Graham Hancock's
latest work ancient apocalypse so there
is this uh deliberate
there is this this uh pattern of
behavior that you see among these
researchers
um including Graham Hancock of of
deliberately not speaking about India of
deliberately uh not telling the world
about
the truth about India or anything about
India at all just don't speak about
India speak about Egypt and speak about
Mesopotamia and and uh gigantia in in in
Malta speak out the Inca Aztecs in
quotes and uh
uh various other gods speak about gudang
panag in Indonesia yeah speak about
globality
other places but just don't speak about
India which is well it obviously speaks
about a certain bias that these people
have and the reason why you see Grand
man [\h__\h] is an important uh researcher I
don't agree with everything he says but
he does make some good points but you
know a lot of the uh mainstream
interpretations are incredibly correct
uh in are totally incorrect I beg your
pardon totally incorrect
um there is a lot of group think in
archeology there is a refusal to see
facts and to and to interpret things
properly uh and so on so forth so that
also applies to India so certain things
are true uh he has been talking about
the younger dryas impact hypothesis
which kind of has a lot of uh evidence
that supports it you know of late a lot
of evidence has emerged that does
support what he has been talking about
for a long time so it's good to see that
part of what he has been claiming
Vindicated but there is a lot that he
that lot that he speaks about that
doesn't make sense first of all he
speaks he makes the claim over and over
and over again that there was one single
ancient highly technologically advanced
civilization from which everything else
emerged
he says that before the younger riots
Dryer's impact before the Calamity at
the end of the last ice age there was
before that a very highly
technologically advanced civilization
that's what he says it's possible
but the theory that he has put forth is
it's termed the the term that's used for
it is hyper diffusionism
hyper diffusionism which what is what
does it mean what does this term mean so
hyper diffusionism means that it is the
claim that certain cultural traits
certain intellectual advancements
certain scientific advancements in
certain Technologies
originated in a single
culturally and overall technologically
advanced civilization just one
civilization
and then all these things that spread to
other cultures from this one
civilization this is called hyper
diffusionism
and that is totally pseudocide of
scientific
where is your evidence that there was
just one Advanced civilization why not
five Advanced cultures or seven Advanced
cultures why just one
you know so that doesn't make any sense
whatsoever there is zero evidence that
supports this claim and yet he keeps on
repeating this claim over and over again
so there is a lot to admire about the
guy and there is a lot that the guide is
completely wrong about or at least he
doesn't make any sense there are so many
leaps of imagination that that are not
support that are completely unsupported
by data and there is a very curious uh
insistence on on on my on not speaking
about India
you you go across the globe you go to
Mexico you go to South America you go to
the Caribbean you go to Bimini you go to
Egypt you go to Indonesia you go to
Malta you go to Turkey you go all across
the world but you refuse to go to India
which is known to be the most ancient
civilization so yeah this smacks of bias
and so that's why what purnima is saying
is entirely correct so
so you know Grandma and [\h__\h] is
important it is worthwhile to study
his writings his research but
it doesn't fill all the gaps and it it
uh I am not I have not read all his
books yeah I just have one right now
it's about uh it's about America
so that's something I still have to read
but yeah so I think it's worthwhile to
study his work and to read his work but
it the one has to be careful because a
lot of his assumptions are incorrect a
lot of his assumptions are are of of are
something that comes out of his
imagination
unsupported by data
but yeah it's it's uh certainly
worthwhile to study his work to fill in
some of the gaps and some understanding
that we may have
okay saurabh says did harappans know how
to perform brain as well as dental
surgery
some finding points out this consensus
all right harappans and surgery
um we do know
but I mean look the harappans are not
some extinct people yes
so when we talk about did the harappans
do this or did harapas do that we are
talking about our ancestors
the harappans were not some people who
disappeared
it was not some civilization that
existed and it no longer exists it is a
continuation we today are a continuation
of the so-called Harappan or Indus
Valley people
right
it is the same civilization it's a
today's India is a continuation of that
Civilization
so it was one phase
a specific phase of the 10 000 plus year
old Indian civilization that was the
so-called Harappan period so the people
of that time those the people our
ancestors who lived at the time we know
that they did perform various kinds of
surgery let's see what kind of surgery
they performed they shall we
let me put something on the screen
here we are
excuse me so this is
um a news report
dig uncovers ancient roots of Dentistry
proving prehistoric men's Ingenuity to
blah blah blah blah so uh researchers
have found that Dental drilling drilling
dates back 9000 years
so they talk about Pakistan which is
obviously temporarily the separate
nation but it is uh our ancestral land
and part of the satta Sindhu region
where our ancestors lived during the
so-called where some of our ancestors
live during the so-called Harappan
period yeah
so uh
so they have they have discovered
evidence of ancient Dentistry that dates
back
around 9000 years
which is temporarily part of Pakistan
yeah
so uh
so they what's written here is that
primitive dentists drilled nearly
perfect holes into live but undoubtedly
unhappy patients between 5500 BC and
7000 BC and so on so forth yeah
researchers carbon dated at least nine
skulls with 11 drill holes found in a
in a graveyard in this region they call
it Pakistan and so on so yeah here's an
example of a tooth that was drilled very
very well drilled tooth almost perfect
holes and all that and this is a
reconstruction or Recreation of what was
done at the time by our ancestors
so we know that our ancestors from the
so-called Harappan period knew how to uh
perform a dental surgery did they do
this or without anesthesia I mean
so that article assumes that it was done
without anesthesia but that's an
assumption that has no basis in fact
we've had uh the ancient system of
ayurveda and all that which was very
Advanced it's possible that we had the
painkillers of various kinds that were
used to maybe number the part of the
truth the part of the Joe locally and
and provide some relief from the parent
and so on but yeah
that's beside the point so yes our
ancestors from that time knew how to
perform dental surgery I am not sure
about brain surgery we know there was a
ancient practice of trepidation that was
performed by ancient peoples much before
much older than the that uh than our
ancestors from the Harappan times yeah
uh trepidation was when you drill a
small circular hole into the brain of an
individual of a live individual so
sometimes what happens is that you know
there are
cranial injuries head injuries somebody
falls down from a tree for instance or
from a cliff you're claiming to to
gather honey and you fall from there you
fall 10 feet 20 feet or whatever you
bang your head and what happens is that
the brain swells up inside there is
pressure that builds up and that can
sometimes kill people so one of the ways
of relieving that is to drill a hole or
something to relieve the pressure so
people archaeologists have found many
ancient skulls in various parts of the
world with those uh trepidation uh sort
of procedures visible in that you know a
hole that was drilled and then you can
see that the bone has healed around it
which means that they that the person
lived and survived the procedure
I'm not sure if they have found that
sort of thing in in the Sarasota Hindu
region maybe they have I have not come
across it myself as far as I can
remember but yes uh I think that if
ancient peoples
you know from the Primitive
hunter-gatherer times apparently were
able to do it then I'm sure that our
ancestors in the Sarasota Sindhu region
would have had better procedures for for
a cranial surgery possibly brain surgery
we don't have evidence as far as I know
but it is certainly possible but we do
have very clear evidence of dental
surgery proper dental surgery being
performed proper drilling of holes very
rapidly very rapid drilling of holes and
good you know precise holes being
drilled into people's teeth about nine
thousand years before today yeah so that
indicates that technology was Advanced I
mean to a certain degree nine thousand
years before today
so yeah that tells you about the kind of
uh
lives our ancestors lived in this region
all those years ago
so that's what I can tell you
okay pujan says
you have talked about the sunken city of
dwarka before that is being found uh
still why don't we get much news proper
images or documents about it I also also
I heard that the ASI archaeological
study of Survey of India has stopped
doing more research there shouldn't we
study those ruins
to get a better idea about our ancient
India I think we should study those
ruins to get a better idea of ancient
India you know it's it's it's
disappointing and it's perplexing
that somebody like Grandma Hancock which
whom we just spoke about just a minute
ago someone like him
with the help of private funds with the
help of Netflix or whoever has helped
him to make the movie he has been able
to go across the world to seven or eight
ancient sites with high technology with
drones with leader the the technology
that helps you peer under the ground and
discern what kind of structures lie
below the surface of the Earth several
tens of meters below the Earth he has
access to that technology he has access
to sonar technology that allows you to
to map the the the seabed the ocean
floor you know so a guy a private a
private individual and a private
filmmaking company with whatever
productive production producer he has
was able to acquire all this technology
and and show so much detail in that TV
series ancient apocalypse
with just private funding in the case of
the ASI they have the the funding that
comes from the government of India one
of the most powerful and richest
governments in the world
and still we have no idea of what lies
below the surface of the ocean
no images have been released whatever
images were released were from 20 30
years ago it is so disappointing that
the ASI is not doing this they have the
funds if they don't have the funds
publicize it
the government has the money
the government has the money to do this
I would like to say the ASI the first of
all the Asis is
I've said this so many times I think the
ASI is is incompetent
I'm sure there are some good
archaeologists in the ASI we know in the
past there have been some really good
archaeologists
comes to mind and obviously uh Dr
bibilal one of the greatest
archaeologists the world has ever seen
yes two such uh very prominent people
come to mind so the ASI I'm sure even
today would have some good
archaeologists but overall it's a bunch
of bureaucrats who run the show
yeah and we know what the ESI is doing
so many temples under its its protection
they have been plundered the idols have
been stolen they end up in in Western uh
auction houses
we can see online auctions of of
Sarasota Sindhu artifacts happening all
over the world
yes there are various there is a site
called vatican.com in which you can see
it I wonder where those artifacts are
being plundered from some of them would
be plundered from the Pakistani side of
the Sarasota Hindu region but I expect
some of them would be planted from the
Indian part as well which is which would
which would come under ASR protection
there are so many articles I can put on
the screen
that attest to the fact that ASI
protected monuments are being plundered
the ASI is incompetent I think the ASI
should be disbanded and the money should
be reinvested in creating into creating
a Professional Organization run by
professionals not by bureaucrats
incompetent bureaucrats
so that's the first thing I would like
to say the ASI needs to be disbanded and
a new Professional Organization needs to
be created which is which which has
dedicated professional archaeologists
who are dedicated to their work and then
we need to identify the sites that
really need to be preserved and
investigated
instead of instead of renovating and
protecting and embellishing turkic
monuments the The Monuments
that testify to the Past Millennium of
humiliation of India we should look into
this the sites like dwarka Etc you know
there is an ancient uh City complex in
the Gulf of hambat
not just one
archaeological site but a whole cluster
of archaeological sites under the ocean
30 40 meters below below the surface of
the ocean on the seabed this
uh complex this archaeological
archaeological complexes at least at
least
9 to 11 to 12 000 years old it's a it's
a cluster of ancient cities
that our ancestors built you know and
what's being done there nothing no
investigation whatsoever why don't they
use sonar to map the seabed and and
produce proper images of what the the
the site looks like those archaeological
sites look like why don't we see new
images proper image of images of dwarka
the entire layout of the of the ancient
city nothing is being done it is so
frustrating
so yeah if if a private individual with
limited access to money and funds like
Graham Hancock can produce such a
wonderful documentary a very well
produced documentary like like ancient
apocalypse why can't the ASI or the
government of India do something about
these ancient sites and let the public
know let the people of India know and
the world know what lies below the ocean
what did the ancient
city of dwarka the underwater submerged
city of dwarka look like what did it
look like when it was above the ocean or
at least show us the layout of the city
the architecture and the the the the the
the map of the ancient city and how how
it would perhaps look like you know
and and the in the Gulf of combat
archaeological complex
why why can't we do it it's so
frustrating we have the funds we have
the money
we have an organization like the ASI
ah I just don't get it very frustrating
okay roshni says you have said that
you have said that the Indian population
doesn't have Neanderthal DNA and that it
is one of the things that disproves the
Aryan Invasion Theory I did a DNA test
with 23andMe and the results came back
as 100 Indian mostly mostly North and
also that I have more Neanderthal DNA
than 81 of 23andMe users my dad has more
than 91 percent of users this is
perplexing to me most users in 23andMe
are European of European origin ancestry
is there an alternative explanation to
this
okay so what I had said I did say that
apparently the majority of the Indian
population has almost no Neanderthal
ancestry this is something that Dr
neeraj Rai had said now the research is
not out yet so it's something that was
said verbally we still have to see the
actual result research paper which has
still not been published so we are
waiting for that to happen maybe this
year maybe next year all that stuff will
be published we are waiting for it
um those are going to be very important
papers the paper about the
um about how much Indian Earth our
ancestry exists or does not exist within
India and the paper about the origin of
the r1a haplogroup these are very
important works that are due to be
published reasonably soon now
has said this on multiple occasions that
Indians mostly don't have Neanderthal
ancestry now
let's understand what that means most
Indians have almost no near the ancestry
or negligible Neanderthal ancestry it
doesn't mean that all Indians have zero
Neanderthal ancestry Indians are an
enormous population 1.3 billion people
within present-day India itself if we
put together the entire Indian
subcontinent it's more than it's more
than how much one more than 1.7 billion
in Indians or individuals who are of
Indian ancestry that is an enormous
population group it is a substantial
portion of all Humanity
now you go back two thousand three
thousand years five thousand years to
the Neanderthals went extinct
around 30 to 20 000 years before today
and the easternmost evidence of
Neanderthal uh of them having lived
somewhere is in the Middle East in
Israel you go east further east from
that you see no traces of nearthal uh
near North ever having existed there so
that tells us at the Neanderthals did
not go further east from the Middle East
region from Israel they did not Venture
into let's say Iraq Mesopotamia or Iran
or the Indian subcontinent right
um and they seem to have died out maybe
30 000 years ago or maybe about 20 to 23
000 years before today roughly let's say
20 000 years before today
now we know the Out of Africa migration
happened and at some point in time our
ancestors see our hands we know that the
Out of Africa migrants which migrated
Out of Africa about 80 or 70 000 years
before today they went eastwards they
crossed a map we haven't opened the map
yet how can it be where's the map
here is the map I must show the map I
cannot have a session
without showing the map
ah ah finally the map
um
so most likely the Out of Africa
migration happened over here you see
Djibouti
across this trade which is called the
Baba al-mandib Strait
at some point in time it was possible to
cross this or maybe they used boats or
rafts or whatever so they crossed over
into the um into the Arabian peninsula
they went
eastwards and northwards towards Muscat
presently Muscat towards president Dubai
and then they Pro they crossed over from
here the Strait of Hormuz into what is
now Iran and then they went further
eastwards into Balochistan and then they
entered the Indian subcontinent that is
what most likely happened that's what
genetics and other evidence also tells
us yeah and then from India
they eventually started expanding across
Eurasia East North West everywhere so
India was the first Out of Africa found
a Zone and then as they went westwards
they encountered the Neanderthals and
then there was some intermixing and as a
result of that uh most non-african
humans
have between two to four or two to six
percent Neanderthal ancestry it's like
having one great grandparent or
something who was Neanderthal roughly
like that
a give or take now so some portion of
you of humanity non-african Humanity
has Neanderthal ancestry and some
doesn't
so those who stayed back in the Indian
subcontinent at that point in time would
have had no Neanderthal ancestry then
the Neanderthals go extinct about 20 000
or so years ago and then what you have
is that you have all kinds of migrations
the story of humanity is the story of
migrations there have been lots of
migrations out of India into India and
so on so forth it's it's multiple pulses
and waves of migrations back and forth
back and forth the Indian subcontinent
was the major uh founder Zone most of
humanity at some point in time lived or
most of the non-african humans at some
point in time lived in the Indian
subcontinent and we know there were lots
of migrations out of India and then
there was some back reaction as well
like we say in physics some people
re-entered India at their response in
time we know that the scithians were of
Indian ancestry and at some point in
time about 2000 years ago they
re-entered India they lived all across
the central Asia Eurasia even Eastern
Europe so they would have acquired
Neanderthal ancestry then they
re-entered India about 2000 years ago
and I'm sure lots of people in northern
and western India have some fractional
skit in ancestry we know the Greeks also
lived in Northwest India and I'm sure
lots of people in Northwest India in
Western India Northern India would have
a little bit maybe one person two
percent Greek ancestry as well the
Greeks they lived all of all across near
all the way across in Europe they would
have had near the Thailand history and
so on and so on so forth so there are
lots of these small
waves of migrations back and forth by
back and forth migrations that would
bring in all kinds of mixed ancestry
into India overall if you see the
India's genetics they are very much
Indian genetics but there will be these
minor components that have come from
outside
so most likely the people who live in
Northern India who have had more
exposure to skin and kushan and Greek
ancestry
compared to the people who live in
eastern or Southern India maybe they
would have had they would have more near
the ancestry I would not say that all of
them would have it so if so that's what
I mean right so if you look at the
Indian population as a whole
the entire 1.3 billion strong population
of India and then you do a statistical
analysis and you see how much of
percentage has near neutral ancestry
substantially enough of ancestry or or
non-trivial non-negligible industry you
will see maybe one percent or two person
may have it and roshni it may happen
that you are one of the lucky views the
one of those lucky if you who have
substantial Neanderthal ancestry so you
know that's how it happens you have to
look at it statistically and then you
have to look at it from from an
individual perspective so statistically
when we talk about India there appears
to be and the paper has not been
published yet but whenever it's
published it will show you that
statistically as a whole
the 1.3 billion strong Indian population
seems to have very little Neanderthal
ancestry but individuals will always be
Exceptions there will always be
individuals who will Who will differ
from the from the average right so that
is the explanation that's the
explanation
I don't know what sort of ancestry I
have if I do my 23andMe thing who knows
what it will throw up you know and so on
so individuals
can differ from the norm but overall
statistically it tells you a whole
certain story about these statistical
overall population of India
all right
okay Astra games says your views on
Turks having 18 South Asian
Indian
DNA I despise this fake made up term
South Asia
map
where's the map
take a look at the map of Asia this is
Asia it's actually Eurasia there is no
actual distinction between Europe and
Asia but uh you know the the
it's a it's a eurocentric term
so there is a continent called Eurasia
and what's south of Eurasia
I mean how does India become South Asia
it makes no sense
if you're talking about the south of
Asia even Iran would be in the south of
Asia
and I would say that Indonesia is even
more south of south of Asia so this term
is a fake made up term the correct term
is Indian subcontinent
so
what are my views on Turks having 18
Indian DNA or Indian subcontinental DNA
is it because of slavery and intermixing
with populations at the time of
invasions in India or what exactly it is
so I haven't seen
any news report or any research that
says that Turks have approximately 18
Indian DNA but assuming you are right
what could be the explanation for that
so in case they have discovered that the
people of turkey the Turkish people have
approximately 18 Indian DNA I would not
be surprised at all
to understand why we have to look at the
origin or the the history the story of
the Turkish people the turkic people
so what is the story of the turkic or
Turkish people the origin of the turkic
people is most likely in in
this region which is roughly the region
of Mongolia that's where the there was
this ancient people called the show new
s-i-o-g-n-u or something whatever the
spelling is
s-i-x-i-o-n-g-n-u sure knew these people
they emerge from here they were the the
Chinese call them the show new and later
they were called the Huns right so the
horns are the most likely uh
the most likely progenitors or origin of
the Mongolian and the turkic peoples
so these shown you were a very very
warlike people about two and a half or 2
300 years ago they emerged out of this
region and they started rampaging across
the world yeah
and it triggered off two big invasions
into India firstly this case in Invasion
and then the kushan invasion and this
they harmoniously assimilated into the
Indian population yes they displaced the
Greeks also
later you had these waves of hunnic
invasions hunnic attempts to invade
India starting around the Gupta period
about 1500 1600 years before today and
the great emperor Gupta spent his entire
life repulsing this hunnic invasions
these Invaders were called the shweta
hunas the whitehones and these invasions
were these homes were attempting to
invade India at the same time that they
were attempting to invade Rome the Roman
Empire as well so there were nomadic
period people who whose presence spanned
the whole of Eurasia yeah the horns
eventually after the decline of the
Gupta Empire the horns were able to make
inroads into India
and they do became indianized they they
rule over parts of India Northern India
Etc uh gandhar Afghanistan present day
temporarily Pakistan and various parts
of North India even all the way up to up
to Western India you know the Gujarat
Rajasthan region as well so you had
homic origin Kings ruling these places
and they very rapidly became indianized
they became entirely Indian yes and then
there were there was this Hindu Shahi
Dynasty in Northern India in Afghanistan
and Pakistan present the Pakistan
present-day North India and then the
Kabul shines as well these were hunnic
Kings hunnic dynasties that ruled these
regions they were all either Hindu or
Buddhists the Kabul shais were Hindus I
believe
and they actually for a significant
period of time
repulsed turkic attempts to invade India
those these turkey attempts were Islamic
attempts because these these homes they
later became became the origin of The
Originators of the turkic peoples and
the Turks eventually became islamized
over a period of time that's a whole
different story I'll not go there but
you can look it up
so these homes these hunnic Kings
who were hunic and turkic in origin they
were Hindu Buddhist what it's the same
thing right and they
tried their best to safeguard India from
the turkic invasions which were their
fellow trucks who were Islamic in origin
who are Islamic in in nature character
in religion yeah so um
so that is one interesting story now
these Turks
the Turks who who tried to invade India
beginning about a thousand years ago
they came from various parts of Central
Asia now let's understand what central
Asia was there are two major regions in
Central Asia which is this the
present-day xinjiang region of China
currently part of China for now and the
western part of Central Asia so the
xinjiang part of China which is
currently part of China or China was
originally known as uttarakuru and what
is now Turkmenistan Uzbekistan all that
was at that time in the past known as
uttara madra these were Indian regions
these they were Indian origin Kings and
dynasties and people who lived there so
the whole of Central Asia was
essentially Indian in origin in nature
in culture
you will still find ruins of ancient
Hindu temples who which in in stupas and
all kinds of things all across Central
Asia even in Armenia and so on yeah
so the Turks they conquered all these
regions they they would have indulged in
the standard turkic atrocities but yes
they would also have intermingled with
these people and they would have
acquired their genetics as well
so assuming they're killed of all the
males and and then they they procreated
with the women which is standard
practice for these these people then
they would have acquired Indian DNA
through that through through that
through that uh medium through that
means whatever you want to call it
so it's not surprising that they would
have the substantial percentage of
Indian DNA that is one way it could have
happened and then we know that um that
the Turks then started trying to enter
Anatolia which was then the part of the
Byzantine Empire the Eastern Roman
Empire and eventually after a certain
certain period of time
they did succeed they eventually took
Constantinople yes
and then this region became turkey it
was always historically Greek or
Byzantine Eastern Roman yes
and then the whole different story
happened and so uh that would explain
their their Central Asian origin would
explain why they would have
approximately 18 or whatever percentage
of Indian origin DNA it is not
surprising or perplexing at all
you would also find uh if if proper
research is done lots and lots of Indian
origin
uh Indian DNA in the peoples of the
Arabian part of the world the Middle
East even Egypt even Eastern Africa and
what not a lot more once the research is
done you will find all of these truths
tumbling out
and then there are different stories
associated with each place as to how
this Indian DNA in progressed into these
populations a whole different story you
know if you study the ancient history of
Ethiopia
you will realize that Ethiopia was also
once very much Indian
then
yeah it's a different story it's a whole
different story all right next
all right thank you how exactly is
America in the west declining what are
the causes for it and how will it affect
India and the rest of the world will
this decline of American hegemony be a
net positive for the world so uh yeah I
do say all the time that the West is
declining so why do I say this what are
what's the evidence that the West is
declining so look
there are so many different ways in
which this decline manifests itself
first of all you we do see the rise of
competing economies we see the rise of
competing Powers which was not there 20
30 years ago
yes you are seeing these new power
centers emerge there is China there's
India these are major economies that
have risen over over time India is still
Rising India is still not nowhere close
to China
but yeah we are seeing the rise of
competing economists competing with the
West in the U.S and these are not just
competing economies these are competing
Powers they are competing Powers China
India Iran to some extent is still there
yeah
and then you have the ongoing Revival of
Russia body sales in purposefully
destroyed the Russian economy
starting 20 years ago Vladimir Putin's
to put set off a process of rebuilding
the Russian economy and the the nation
overall and now we can see the the
significant Revival of Russia that's
happening so that's so that is something
we are seeing and in parallel to all
this we are seeing a slowing down in
decline of the U.S economy and the
Western economy we are seeing that
happen we are seeing that happened in
front of our eyes we also see that the
East the Eastern world is now becoming a
hub of Science and Technology and
Innovation and Entrepreneurship it's
happening it's mostly in China in in in
various Eastern nation Nations the
so-called Asian tigers and also now in
India as well now that things have
things have things are changing so we
see that the East is becoming a hub of
all of this science Technology
Innovation entrepreneurship all that the
East now you see it's visible the East
has more energy and more optimism and
more hope you don't see that in the West
yeah and you also see the decline the
slow gradual decline of Western
technological and scientific Primacy
there was a time when all the scientific
advancements all the technology it all
came from the West now it's not the case
now it's not the case we are seeing a
decline in Western technological and
scientific superiority and Primacy
then you have all these societal issues
in the west there is a declining TFR
total fertility rate
um the the birth rates they are
declining drastically in the west and
then you have the clear loss of of of of
cultural and moral and ethical anchors
which is obviously the the users the
prime example of that is the decline the
the wholesale rejection of Christianity
because see
the West
for the past roughly 1500 or 1000 plus
years has been questioned
it's a Christian civilization if you if
you want to call it a civilization right
so the the the the moral and the moral
values the values that the West had
until recently were Christian values now
that is being destroyed that's why the
Christians are trying to now you know uh
convert the east
and that's why there are billions and
billions of billions of dollars being
poured into India for instance for these
purpose of conversion and all that
that's happening as we know so so we are
seeing see
30 years ago when the pope would visit
some part of Europe or whatever there
will be thousands of people lining the
streets
yeah the pope would be treated as a huge
celebrity and some figure worthy of
incredible adulation today the pope goes
somewhere there's no one who comes out
to to to to greet him and and to see his
his car go around the streets you can
see the decline
of Christianity in the West
you see that then you also have the
destruction of the family system of
family values it's it's ongoing in the
west very high divorce rates in the west
single families rampant everywhere
single families you have so much rampant
crime gun violence homelessness child
abuse good God
yeah you can see that and then there is
this new religion in the U.S called
vocism yeah that's there then
then there's a decline of the education
system drastic lowering of standards in
the education system the rise of these
made up degrees I mean if you have a
degree in gender studies what are you
going to produce
you've got if you acquire a degree a
college degree Universal degree it
should it should make you a productive
member of society you should be able to
produce something that provides value to
society if you have a degree in gender
studies or God knows what else what do
you produce you produce nothing
so that's what's happening now all these
made up fake fictitious degrees that
provide no value to society yes and
obviously there's the end of meritocracy
in in the West in education
which also which is something you're
also seeing you can go to social media
and look it up what's happening there in
the education system yeah
and then there is the realization in the
society in the west that the in some
members of society that the entire
Western edifice is built upon
plunder and slavery and genocide and
they are now realizing that the West has
no claim to moral superiority over any
other part of the world
so all of this
is indicative of the very clear ongoing
decline of the West it's happening these
are the causes and these are the
symptoms it's all happening
um how will it affect India and the rest
of the world it's it's it's
driving this ongoing geopolitical
realignment in which the East is rising
there is this new clamor for within all
these nations to join the bricks plus
grouping
um people are hedging their bets nations
are hedging their bets and Nations no
longer believe that they can rely upon
the U.S to give them security long-term
security and all that the EU was
beginning to realize what's happening
and so on so uh it's going to lead
possibly to a period of chaos to a
period of of a lot of instability in the
world maybe a period of war and God
knows what we still don't know I don't
see you I don't know what the future is
going to be like but it looks like there
is an ongoing polarization of the world
an ongoing realignment of the world
order
an ongoing bifurcation of the global
system on the one hand you have the old
obsolete so-called rules-based World
Order on the other hand we have this new
grouping that's emerging very powerful
grouping not yet very powerful but it's
a very important grouping already bricks
Plus
which is the core group of countries is
India Russia China yeah Iran wants to
join uh the Saudis want to join if Iran
and Saudi join then it's going to be a
big deal and so on so we are witnessing
this real this ongoing realignment of
the world the bifurcation of the global
order and so much more so this decline
of the American hegemony I think
um
I think overall it
it will be a net positive for the world
if there is an alternative leader that
emerges and a leader who is not
hegemonic and imperialistic and
oppressive and and rapacious like the
like the Anglo-Saxons have been the past
four 500 years the Anglo-Saxons have
ruled the world it's just one Empire it
was a British Empire then it's the
American Empire now these are two
manifestations of the same entity of the
same thing the same Force the
Anglo-Saxon Empire it's ruled the world
for the past four three four five
hundred years and it's been terrible for
the world it's destroyed the world it
has siphoned off the world's wealth and
and placed it into in the in the hands
of the West and it's destroyed the rest
of the world
it's been very bad for civilization and
for world for the world and for Humanity
so if a different kind of leadership
emerges
then it would be good for the world but
if you have the rise of China for
instance which has the same kind of
Imperial Ambitions then nothing much
will change
nothing much will change overall it'll
still go the same way
but if something like if if a nation
like India manages somehow
to emerge as the leader then maybe
things will change but first India will
have to change itself because right now
India is itself not ruled well you know
what the problems in India are yeah
so yeah that's the deal
that's a deal
um avoid says it's been more than a
month since Mr Rishi suno became the
became the president of the UK
it's it's a very short period of time
but what do you think of him as the
president I think Mr is yeah he has been
president of the UK for for
a week uh well see as the president of
the UK you are actually not very
important whether you are the president
of the UK see if he is the if
the UK's leader president like you say
is an insignificant person there isn't
he or she doesn't really hold any real
power
the UK is a vasal state of the U.S the
real power lies in the U.S whoever
becomes president of the UK just does
what he or she is told like a good boy
or good girl and uh
so as you can see Mr ruhi sanak is in
his capacity as president of the UK has
been going to the G20 Summit he was very
happy there uh you can see he's smiling
and beaming he also made his way to
Ukraine where he met the great uh actor
Mr zelinski yeah and he met Mr Macau and
all that so he's he's getting used to
being a world leader and all that but he
is a leader Only Name the president of
the UK is not
is not uh someone who holds the real
power the real power resides somewhere
far away somewhere across the pond like
they like they say across the Atlantic
Ocean yeah uh so um so the real power
lies if more in Washington if you're the
prime minister of the US then you may
have more power the president of the UK
doesn't have so much power so overall I
don't care about Mr Rishi sunak may be a
good guy I I think overall it's better
him than somebody else from our
perspective at least it's an Indian
origin person but it doesn't really
matter much
it makes lots of Indians happy good for
them enjoy it I'm not sure how long he
will last as the president of the UK as
long as the prime minister of the US
wants him to last I assume so yeah
that's that's what I can say about how
about this matter
next question
the next question
I wait for it to come
sorry where is it here it is Mother
Chacha says why does hunger persist in
the world today despite the fact that
humans have achieved so much of
prosperity over the decades what are the
ways to eradicate hunger do you think
hunger can be eliminated from the world
through philanthropy you know we already
have the means and the money and the
resources to eradicate all world hunger
there is so much wealth and prosperity
in the West
yeah
I have the money they have the resources
to immediately within within a week
eradicate all world hunger they don't
want to
because they stay Rich at the expense of
the rest of the world at the expense of
the so-called Global south or the third
world especially Africa
you know what the British did in India
how did the indu how did they engineer
these artificial famines we had so much
incredibly fertile land in India like we
do still do yeah but they they forced
the Indian Farmers to grow cash crops
instead of food crops
so they forced Indian Farmers to grow
Indigo for instance or they forced
Indian Farmers to grow opium
or something else
but not food crops
and then what and obviously there would
still be food that would be cultivated
but that would be shipped off somewhere
else and so on so the British created
this art engineer these artificial
famines in India right now
in Africa
there are so there is so much coffee
being being uh
being planted being cultivated coffee
has been cultivated and uh
things like that and various other other
luxury crops have been cultivated for
European consumption
if the African leaders were to refuse
and say that we will not
cultivate these crops anymore we will
cultivate let's say wheat or rice or
whatever else then those African leaders
will be deposed there will be a color
Revolution and they'll be bummed off and
then another pliable leader will be
installed and then the same thing
continues that's how they deliberately
keep Africa dirt poor
that's what the the West is doing
this poverty that you see in Africa and
certain other nations it is artificially
induced poverty
Africa is still mostly entirely almost
entirely colonized even today
what the East Union company and the
British Raj were doing in India the past
300 years you're still seeing the very
same things happening in Africa today
that's why there is so much destitution
and poverty and hunger in Africa
you see that's that's what's happening
it can all be eliminated the Europeans
need to get out of Africa stop
interfering in the internal affairs of
African nations let them resolve their
differences and go on with their lives
on their own without external
interference but that won't happen right
that's what's happening
most African nations have corrupt
dictators ruling them
these corrupt dictators are allowed to
rule despite you know the West talks
about democracy and human rights they
have all these World indices and all
that
and yet they tolerate this they don't
tolerate it they ensure there is no
democracy in Africa they ensure there
are corrupt dictators ruling African
nations so that because they benefit
from this that's the reason why there is
so much suffering and hunger and poverty
and destitution in the in the world it
is all engineered being engineered
actively as we speak right now by
various Western powers
that's what's happening
okay Mona Lisa says
um what's the agreement with the USA
regarding ESO and why did we do it
do we have any agreement with the USA
vis-a-vis ISRO
um see I'm not sure if we have any
specific one agreement with U.S about
with regarding Israel I think India and
the us or ISRO and NASA for instance
have had this uh
history of ongoing cooperation and
collaboration in a variety of ways for
instance we all know about mangalyan
chandraya and Etc the first chandrayaan
mission was launched I think in 2008 or
something yes
um chandrayaan one and it was a
successful Mission the the satellite the
the spacecraft was in orbit around the
Moon it did a lot of good work it's
still around there but it's dead now uh
it's run out of power
so on chandrayaan one we had I believe
two American instruments the Moon
mineralogy mapper was one and the other
was a a miniature synthetic aperture
radar so two instruments came from NASA
they were installed on chandrayaan one
and the other thing was that General one
had this uh instrument called the moon
impact probe which was an impactor which
went and slammed into the moon's surface
around the South Pole region I believe
of the Moon
and then there was another NASA
satellite that picked up a
and no I think it was chandran itself
which then analyzed The Cloud of debris
that came out of the impact
when this impactor hit the moon slammed
into the moon with high velocity it it
it threw off this huge plume of debris
boom like that and then chandrayaan what
it did was it it analyzed the debris and
it discovered there is water in the
debris and that was the first
confirmation that there is water on the
moon
it was done by chandrayaan 1 and there
was a NASA involvement in that so
that's one example and when it comes to
chandrayaan 2 which was launched in 2019
I think uh it was a partial success the
Lander did not work it
it
crashed onto the moon surface at the
very last moment it went upside down I
will yeah
so on that it sell on that too there was
I believe a laser retro reflector which
was provided by the Americans yeah it's
a device that reflects light back to its
source with very little scattering so if
you are sitting on Earth and you are
aiming at the at that instrument on the
moon with a laser beam then within I
think two or three seconds the laser
beam beam comes back to you and you can
do various tests using that yeah so that
laser retro reflector was also provided
by the Americans so there is this
history of ongoing cooperation between
America and India in the space program
India is not yet a huge competitor to
the U.S so they are happy to to
collaborate in a in a variety of ways if
India becomes a major space Power like
it has the potential to be then maybe
it's so much cooperation may not happen
or maybe it will will see how it goes
yep
so that's what it is so I'm not aware of
any single or specific agreement between
India and the US regarding Israel but
there is a history a long long history
of ongoing cooperation and collaboration
between ISRO and NASA and India and the
US in the field of space space
exploration yeah
Karthik says if we cannot see what is
outside the observable universe how did
the James Webb Space Telescope capture
the first galaxies of the after the big
bang
it's because the first galaxies that
emerged out after the big bang are part
of the observable universe
they are not outside the observable
universe see you see this ball here
think of it as the observable universe
we are at the center
we are at the very center of it and
after the big bang very very soon after
the big bang
the universe was about this size after
the you know very very soon less than a
second after the big bang and then it
expanded over time and so on and after
about 200 or so million years after the
big bang the first galaxies emerged
and these were inside the universe not
outside the universe they are all part
of the observable universe and because
they are part of the observable universe
that's why the James Webb Space
Telescope has succeeded in in capturing
the four pawns the the infrared light
that came out of those galaxies all
those 13 Point whatever million years
ago 13 point
13.6 or so billion years before today
and that's how the jwst has been able to
capture the light from there so it was
these galaxies were part of the
observable universe they are inside the
observable universe not outside that's
why it is so very interesting science
that's coming out of the jwst and many
challenges they're facing micro
meteoroid impacts and whatnot but
overall it's doing well and uh it's in
the process of Revolution
revolutionizing our understanding of the
universe so yeah great work being done
there
okay Daniel Nicholson says ours being a
three-dimensional world we perceive
length breadth height the fourth
dimension being space space Sorry time
not space time time uh how many
dimensions do we all together have and
without present brain capacities could
we ever imagine of understanding and
feeling all those dimensions so yes uh
the world that we see we perceive it as
being a three-dimensional World length
breadth height three dimensions and then
there is this mysterious thing called
time which in the framework of general
relativity is the fourth dimension so in
general relativity we inhabit a
four-dimensional universe space time
space time and within space time we have
these various phenomena that happen
space time is the stage upon which we
dance upon which the universe dances
yeah
and the curvature of space-time is
perceived as what we perceive as the
force of gravity the
um and so on so forth yeah
um the curvature
of space-time is is what we perceive is
gravity so uh according to general
relativity there are four dimensions
according to our
experienced uh world we have three
dimensions but time is there yeah
now according to um Theory which came
out 100 years ago or so they did
calculations in five Dimensions they
introduced an extra Dimension and that
throughout some interesting results
according to one version of string
theory there are 10 Dimensions according
to another version of string theory
there are 11 Dimensions according to
boson explained the theory there are 26
Dimensions we have never found those
Dimensions yeah
and recently
uh Dr sebastak Who was on this channel
on this on the ability chapter podcast
just a couple of weeks ago he has been
doing very interesting work in the past
two and a half years
and he has demonstrated that the optimal
number of dimensions in the universe is
not two or three or four or whatever it
is e
e is called Euler's number look up what
e is it is an irrational number less
than three but not quite two
yeah so the universe has e dimensions
and that actually kind of resolves many
of the problems and and contradictions
in in physics
so we don't quite know for sure but it's
quite possible the universe has e
dimensions
not three not four not ten not 11 not 26
but e Dimensions that would be weird
right but yeah the world is weird and
that seems to resolve many of the
paradoxes like the Hubble tension like
what what is the like the nature of
gravity and why gravity has had
different strengths at different
epochs of the universe's history it also
kind of kind of throws light upon the
the mysteries of dark matter and dark
energy and so on very interesting
research Dr Clark is doing
yeah so yeah that's kind of what's
happening and uh
very interesting work yeah so yeah
that's what I can say about this but
what about brain capacity and all that
um so imagine there are more than three
or four dimensions let's say there are
10 Dimensions so one of the one of the
things that that's been theorized is
that these dimensions are ultra
microscopic dimensions and curled up so
only if you go into the quantum domain
will you be able to perceive those extra
Dimensions otherwise you will not be
able to perceive them and all that and
so on so yeah it's all theoretical there
is no evidence for that
but that's how they make they have been
able to make string theory work
mathematically by introducing extra
Dimensions we're not sure if they
actually exist possibly there are not
10 Dimensions there are e Dimensions
possibly so it's all still of work in
progress but very interesting work done
by doctor being done by Dr Clark right
now very important and very interesting
book
all right let's take some more questions
a few questions in there pranav says
which books to read to understand power
well typically I don't do book
recommendations because there are so
many caveats you have to give especially
when it comes to books about history but
if you want to talk about books about
power I can give you a couple of
recommendations so let me put uh
let's let's do a Google search shall we
let's do a Google search Let me give you
two book recommendations
one is 48
rules of Power by Brian Greene this is
an interesting book I haven't read it
for more than more than 15 years I would
say but yeah it's a very interesting
book it's about personal power
yeah but it's it's a very what what they
would call a Machiavellian book you know
how to manipulate people and how to
acquire more power at the expense of
others and so on like a zero-sum game at
some at times it's like that and so on
it's an interesting book or it's called
the 48 rules of Power by Brian Greene
that's one possible recommendation the
other is the
dictator's handbook
the dictator's handbook uh why is there
a background backtrack there you go so
this book is by uh two authors one is
Alistair Smith and the other is Bruce
Bueno de Mesquita this is an interesting
book as well this is about political
power it's about more large-scale power
structures and all that
so here are two book recommendations
about power one is Brian green one is
this other one the dictator's handbook
both are interesting books and there are
so many more but yeah you want to start
off start off with these two possibly
and see how it goes for you whether you
like them whether you can make sense of
them or not interesting books about
about power okay let's take
um one more question
says would you like to see your
predictions about Twitter becoming a
trillion dollar company go wrong and
instead witness cool replacing replacing
Twitter worldwide which other
competitors do you see Rising alongside
with cool so I have so so coup is a
Twitter knockoff it's an Indian
social media platform I think I have a
cool account I had made it about two or
three years ago at that time I used coup
for just a while and then I gave up on
it it was very buggy extremely poor user
experience not fun to use at all just to
crash and it was not fun to use Twitter
was so much easier to use so I have a
cool account I haven't used it in close
to two years hopefully it's better now I
I hear that the Brazilians have adopted
coup lots of Brazilians have moved to
cool and uh so on so if it is so good
but I would say that you know
I I hope code as well or or any other
Indian social media startup we need to
have our own platforms and competitors
uh nothing would make me happier than
seeing my prediction go go wrong
and an Indian platform emerging and
becoming a major competitor to Twitter
nothing would make me happier
so I made that prediction based on the
logic I mean based on logic that yeah it
looks like once Elon Musk takes over he
knows how to take a company to the next
level multiple levels and he knows how
to make money he knows how to succeed So
based on his track record it's quite
likely it's quite possible that he may
end up turning Twitter into a trillion
dollar company within the next two to
five years it's very possible let's see
if it happens or not but yeah I would be
happy if an Indian social media platform
were to become a major competitor the
Twitter right now I think who is very
far away from being that I hope the user
experience is better now on cool
but the thing about Twitter is that it's
it's the global uh meeting place you you
can interact with people from all across
the world within five minutes you can
take a pulse of what's Happening across
the world or in a certain country what's
the sentiment the mood of the people
over there right now you can go to
Twitter and immediately see what's
happening in sport let's say or in
politics or in India or in the US what
are the Americans talking about you
don't see that much in KU because the
whole world hasn't adopted coup yet so I
think that uh whoever is running cool or
whatever else needs to be Innovative
don't just create a knockoff or just a
clone of what Twitter is but you know
be Innovative add extra features
something that others don't have and so
on and maybe that that could be more
interesting and make things really work
and really differentiate it from the
existing products yeah so um
that's what I could say about this
um
what else let's take a question from
swapnil Africa is building a great green
wall across the Sahel region from
Senegal to Djibouti to hold back the
advancing Sahara Desert when you succeed
in making the region lush green and
habitable again what is the Sahel region
let's take a look at the map once again
we have
the map on the screen where it is where
is it here it is
the Sahel region is the region between
it's essentially the white part you know
the the the the the transition zone
between the Sahara Desert and the their
remainder of Africa so uh several
African nations are planning to build a
great green wall in this region you know
artificial reforestation or A4
forestation to uh check the advance of
the Sahara Desert will they succeed it's
very possible that they succeed see uh
the advance of a desert is a result of
natural or or whatever climate change
now climate change is a slow gradual
creeping process
but human interventions can can move
much faster than the pace at which
climate change moves so it is definitely
possible if if all these various Nations
come together and act in unison that
they will be able to possibly in the
next 10 or 20 years genuinely create
this entire belt of forest which could
very much end up stopping the advance of
the Sahara Desert and once you create an
artificial Forest the entire climate
change is in the in the region because
forests reduce the temperature you know
uh wherever you have a forest the
temperature drops several degrees maybe
two degrees three degrees four degrees
even depending on the size of the forest
so if you create an artificial Forest
you're gonna create a Zone in Africa
where the temperature is lower which
would bring in rain
which would then expand the forest so it
could end up you know properly checking
the uh the advance of the Sahara Desert
so it is entirely possible that these
nations could succeed if they act in
unison act properly
it's entirely possible they could do it
in the next 20 or so yes very much
possible maybe even 10 years
right
okay I still have lots of other
questions but let me take some questions
from the live chat so in case you all
have questions for me in the live chat
please go ahead and ask me and I shall
take a few
Elon yes Elon is the name
Ellen well maybe all right do we have
questions for me and I shall take some
can you explain about the Crusades well
I would have to take a few hours to
explain what happened there the Crusades
but to explain in a nutshell this was
the attempt by European powers to expand
their hegemony they expand their sphere
of influence into the Middle East so the
Middle East was at the time ruled by the
Arabs by the by the by the Muslims yes
and the the questions called that region
the where very today you have Israel
they called they called it the Holy Land
you know the birthplace of Jesus Christ
uh apparently and all that so they
wanted to reclaim it and bring it under
Christian rule again and that's what it
was all about so various Kings and
rulers of of of uh Europe under the uh
under the banner of the Vatican of the
of the Roman Catholic Church they made
these various incursions into this
region multiple campaigns which were
called the Crusades at some point in the
time it succeeded and eventually it was
it was defeated by by
so that is in very brief about the
Crusades maybe I could take it up in the
future and give a deeper more detailed
explanation I have absolutely heard of
no evidence that our head is older than
the feet
I I I have absolutely no idea about this
how is the head older than the feed in
which way
so yeah sir I'm sorry I may be ignored
okay and I may not know about it I don't
know everything in the world there are
things that I do not know about so maybe
but I have personally never ever come
across a claim that the head is older
than the feet even slightly I never
heard of it sorry
okay somnath says what is Project Khali
by drdo what's the future of directed
energy weapons in India so this is a
story that keeps cropping up
but uh drdo has never made any
pronouncements any announcement of any
such thing
Kali so people speculate about this that
maybe it's some some incredibly powerful
world ending weapon that will
I don't know what it is yeah it it
so have been in the early 2000s some
kind of directed energy weapons program
or some kind of experiment that the kilo
ampere linear uh injector or something I
don't know what it was kilo ampere is a
very very very tiny small amount of
energy yeah kilo ampere very small very
small so um I don't know if it has
evolved or morphed into something major
I have no idea drdo has made no
announcements and made publicized
nothing so the answer is I don't know
it's for drdo if they wish if they
choose to do so to announce
whether something is being done whether
this project still exists
or maybe they should not if it is
something that's sensitive and something
uh
that is important for India's national
security in that case they should not
announce it so the answer from from my
perspective is I don't know because the
government has announced I think drdo
has announced nothing for the past 15
years as far as I know what's the future
of directed energy represent India I
hope the future is good what's a
directed energy weapon
essentially think of a laser a laser is
this pointer that we have which throws
this collimated beam of light uh
um which which doesn't you know diverge
in that manner that's that's what a
laser is
and if you pump in enough energy into
that light it can poke holes through
solid surfaces so that's a directed
energy weapon so you could so today what
you have is that in the 1950s 1960s
1970s you had this James Bond movies in
which you had lasers that could you know
uh cut through metal sheets and all that
so that was
what the that was the promise that
lasers held and today I believe such
lasers do exist and such lasers do have
military applications
so imagine
there's a plane flying in the air and
you shoot a laser at it
so it would poke a hole through the
aircraft and it will crash it or there's
a missile that's coming in and instead
of shooting a missile to intercept that
missile you just fire a laser at it and
it will destroy the missile in mid-air
imagine there's a ballistic missile
coming in at Mac 23 speed and yet if you
have a laser you can you can take it out
so there is a lot of potential military
military
usage potential that lasers and directed
energy weapons have I am not sure what
the status is in India of the research
and development of such weapons I hope
it is being done maybe in drdo maybe
somewhere else but no such announcements
have been made so once again I don't
know but the potential is there so
hopefully this work is being done and
hopefully there is a good future for
that
right okay let's take one more question
if there is something interesting that I
can dig up
um um
what is it where is it where is it do we
have anything interesting
do we have anything interesting
you've said that multipolarity is good
but I I agree but one there'll be
multiple wars in the world due to this
well if you have multipolarity and
everybody wants to kill each other fight
each other then there'll be multiple
Wars even in unipolarity you've seen
Wars but you don't hear about them or
maybe you choose not to look at them how
many wars has the world seen during
during the unipolar and bipolar phase
go and look up a list of U.S
interventions in the world there's a
whole laundry list of wars that they've
created that they've caused
war is has always been a part of
humanity whether it's a unipolar world
or a bipolar world or a multi-polar
world or whatever it is Wars have been
around
so there's nothing you can do about it
so you cannot say that Wars there will
be more Wars because the world will
become multiple or no Wars have always
been around what's happening right now
as we speak we still don't have a
multiple world right now
we still have a mostly unipolar world
right now as we speak and still there
are Wars going on there is Yemen going
on there is there is Ukraine going on
there are conflicts in Africa that you
have not heard about there's the Eritrea
Ethiopia thing going on there is there
is the the Darfur situation in Sudan
there is so much more more happening
that you that you are not aware of
Wars have always been there
so I don't I don't agree that
multi-polarity will cause an upsurge in
the number of conflicts in the world I
don't think so
okay
okay I hope I hope that answer makes
sense
uh
Shaheen is right the history of mankind
is the history of buffet unfortunately
there is a truth yeah
uh all right do we have anything as so
many questions I'm sure I'll be missing
lots of them
couldn't the US be using Saudi Arabia to
get into bricks and get some inner
information out of the means of Saudi
yeah if they're children they would do
it but
that's not how it works you can get
Inner inner information through a
variety of means you don't need to put
Saudi Arabia into brics for that
uh get um anything else
yeah I don't know
are we in Kali yoga yes we are in
kalyuga it's great fun isn't it
uh
do we have any other interesting
questions I have no idea about the kalpa
vigra idol
okay I have no idea about it
sorry some people say it's 39 million
years old some people say it's 27
million thousand years old
an idol a statue made of metal cannot be
dated
how do you date a statue made of metal
you can carbon date something if it has
organic substances metal is an inorganic
substance how do you date that
so if you have a metallic object how
does anybody decide that it's so many
years old
so I see these claims being made that
it's twenty seven thousand or twenty
three thousand or thirty seven thousand
years old or something I have no idea
what is the factual basis on which these
claims are made
and I have not seen any research paper
or any actual any genuine research about
what this Idol is this statue is um
where it's come from or whatever I see
blog posts and various other claims made
on social media and various other things
which cannot be relied upon
where's the primary evidence what's the
primary sources of where it's come so I
have no idea because I've never been
able to find any actual
substantive
research or study
or evidence of what this thing is so so
my answer is I have no idea as to what
this is
um
share my favorite books
too many to share
and it would take a long time
okay
Hindi Channel
when it comes to technical technical
subjects technical matters and then
scholarly matters cookie because my
entire study my entire
education all of that has been in
English that's called mental
colonization maybe in the future maybe
next year I may become more active on
the Hindi Channel maybe maybe I will do
that I I hope to do that I will have to
do some put some things in place for
that but yes that is on my to-do list to
become active on a regular basis on the
Hindi Channel hopefully next year
hopefully very soon
all right I think we are at the end of
today's session so thank you so much all
of you once again for participating for
asking all these questions I apologize
to all of you to the hundreds and
thousands of you who have asked me
questions I've not been able to take
them I always try to take as many as
possible and the best possible questions
and I'll keep on doing this but for now
we are at the end of today's session so
thank you so much everybody once again
very grateful I will see you very soon
in the next live stream until then take
care
and see you bye good night good day see
you later see